okay this
is linear algebra lecture
11 and at the end of lecture
10 I was talking about some Vector
spaces but there the the things in those
Vector spaces were not what we usually
call
vectors nevertheless you could add them
and you could multiply by numbers so we
can call them vectors I think the
example I was working with they were
matrices so the m so we had like a
matrix space the space of all 3x3
matrices and I'd like to just pick up on
that because uh we've been so specific
about n dimensional space here here and
you really want to see that the same
ideas work as long as you can add and
multiply by scalers so these
new new Vector
spaces the example I took was the space
m of all
3x3
matrices
okay I can add the I can multiply by
scalers I can multiply two of them
together but I don't do that that's not
part of the vector space picture the
vector space part is just adding the
matrices and multiplying by numbers and
that's fine we all we stay within this
space of 3x3 matrices and I had some
subspaces that were interesting like the
symmetric the Subspace of symmetric
matrices symmetric
3x3 or the Subspace of upper
triangular
3x3 now
I I use the word
Subspace because it follows the rule
that if I add two symmetric matrices I'm
still symmetric If I multiply two
symmetric matrices is the product
automatically symmetric
no but I'm not multiplying matrices I'm
just adding so I'm fine these this is a
Subspace similarly if I add two upper
triangular matrices I'm still upper
triangular and uh that's a Subspace now
I just want to take these as examples
and ask well what's the basis for that
Subspace what's the dimension of that
Subspace and what's the dimension of the
whole Space
so uh there's a natural basis for all
3x3
matrices and why don't we just write it
down so so M A
basis for
M again all
3x3
okay
and then I'll just count how many
members are in that basis and I'll know
the
dimension and okay it's going to take me
a little
time in fact what is the dimension what
any idea of what I'm what I'm coming up
with next how many numbers does it take
to specify that 3x3
Matrix nine nine is the is the dimension
I'm going to find and the most obvious
basis would be the Matrix that's that
Matrix and then this Matrix with a one
there
and that's two of them so I put in the
third
one and then
onwards and the last one maybe would end
with the one
okay that's like the standard basis in
fact our space is
practically the same as nine-dimensional
space it's just the nine numbers are
written in a square instead of in a
column but somehow it's different and
and ought to be thought of
as uh in sort of natural for itself
because now what about the symmetric
3x3 so that's a
Subspace just let's just think what's
the dimension of that Subspace and
what's a basis for that
Subspace
okay and I guess this question occurs to
me if I look at this Subspace of
symmetric
3x3
well how many of these original basis
members belong to the
Subspace I think only three of them do
that this one is
symmetric this last one is symmetric and
the one in the Middle with a with a one
in that position in the 2 two position
would be symmetric but so I've got three
of these original nine are symmetric
but uh so this is an example
where but that's that's not all right
what's the dimension let's put the
dimensions down dimension of the of m
was
nine what's the dimension of should we
call this
s is what what what's the dimension of
this I'm I'm sort of taking simple
examples where we can we can uh spot the
answer to these questions
so how many if I have a symmetric think
of all symmetric matrices as a
Subspace how many parameters do I choose
in 3x3 symmetric
matrices six right if I choose the
diagonal that's three
and the three entries above the diagonal
then I know what the three entri is
below so the dimension is
six I guess what's the dimension of this
here let's call this space u for upper
triangular so what's the dimension of
that space of all upper triangular
3x3 again
six again
six and
uh but we haven't got a we haven't seen
a b well actually maybe we have got a
basis here for uh the upper triangulars
I guess six of these guys one two three
four and and a couple more would be
upper triangular so there's an
accidental case where the big basis
contains in it a basis for the Subspace
but with the symmetric guy it didn't
happen the symmetric guy the the basis
so you see what a basis is the basis for
the big space we generally need to think
it all over again to get a basis for the
Subspace and then how do I get other
subspaces well uh we spoke before
about uh the Subspace the symmetric
matrices and the upper triangle this is
symmetric
and upper
triangular okay
what's the
uh what's the dimension of that space
what's in that space so what's a m if a
matrix is symmetric and also upper
triangular that makes
it diagonal so this is the same as the
diagonal
matrices diagonal
3x3 and the dimension of
this of s
intersect U right you're okay with that
symbol that's that's the vectors that
are in both s and
U and that's D so s intersect U is the
diagonals and the dimension of the
diagonal matrices is
three and we've got a basis no
problem okay as I write that I think
okay what about
putting get so this is like this
intersection is taking all the vectors
that are in both that are that are
symmetric and also upper triangular now
we looked at the union suppose I take
the matrices that are
symmetric or upper
triangular what why was that no good so
why is why is it no why is why am I not
interested in the
union putting together those two
subspaces so this these are matrices
that are in s or in U or possibly both
so they the diagonals included but
what's bad about
this it's it's not a Subspace it's like
having taking
you know a couple of lines in the
plane and stopping
there a line this is so there's a
three-dimensional Subspace of a
nine-dimensional space there's oh sorry
six there's a six-dimensional Subspace
of a nine-dimensional space there's
another one but they they're headed in
different directions so it we can't just
put them together we have to fill in so
that's what we do to get get this bigger
space that I'll write with a plus
sign this is
combinations of things in s and things
in U okay so that's that's the final
space I'm going to introduce I have a a
couple of subspaces I can take their
intersection and now I'm interested in
not their Union but their sums so this
would be the this is the
intersection and this will be their
sum so what's what do I need for a for a
Subspace
here I take anything in S Plus anything
in
U I don't just take things that are in s
and pop in also separately things that
are in youu this is the sum of
any
element of
s that is any symmetric Matrix
plus
any in U any
element of
U okay now as long as we've got an
example here tell me what we
get if I take every symmetric Matrix
take all symmetric matrices and add them
to all upper triangular
matrices then I've got a whole lot of
matrices and it is a
Subspace and what's it or it's a vector
space and what Vector space would I then
have any idea what what matrices can I
get out of a symmetric plus an upper
triangular I can get anything I get all
matricies I get
all
3x3 it's worth thinking about that it's
just like stretch your mind a little
just a little to
to think of these
subspaces and what their intersection is
and what their sum is and now can I give
you a little oh let's figure out the
dimension so what's the
dimension of S Plus u in this example
is nine cuz we got all three
by3
so the original spaces had the original
symmetric space had Dimension six and
the original upper triangular space had
Dimension six and
actually I'm seeing here a nice
formula that the dimension of
S Plus the dimension of U if I have two
subspaces the dimension of one plus the
dimension of the other other
equals the dimension of their
intersection plus the dimension of their
sum 6 +
6 is 3 +
9 it's kind of satisfying that these
natural operations and we these this is
it actually this is the this is the the
the set of natural things to do with
with subspaces
that uh the dimensions come
out in a good way okay maybe I'll take
just one more example of a vector space
that doesn't have vectors in
it it's it say take come from
differential
equations so this is a one more new
Vector space that we'll give just a few
minutes to suppose I have a differential
equation like DC y
[Music]
dx2 + y =
okay I look at the solutions to that
equation so what are the solutions to
that
equation y
equal cos x is a
solution y = sinx is a
solution y = well e to the IX is a
solution if you want if you allow me to
put that
in oh but why should I put that in it's
already
there I'm you see I'm really looking at
a null space here I'm looking at the
null space of a differential
equation that's the solution
space
and describe the solution space all
solutions to this differential equation
so the equation is y Prime + y =
0 cosine cosine is a solution s is a
solution now tell me all the
solutions there're so I don't need e to
the iix forget that what are all the
what are all the complete
solution
is
what a combination of these the complete
solution is y =
Su multiple of the cosine plus Su
multiple of the
sign that's a vector
space that's a vector space what's the
dimension of that space what's the basis
for that
space okay let me ask you a basis first
if I take the set of solutions to that
second order differential
equation there it is those are the
solutions what's a basis for that
space now remember what's the what
question am I asking because if you know
the question I'm asking you'll see the
answer a basis means all the guys in the
space are combinations of these basis
vectors
well this is a basis sinx cos x there is
a
basis those
two you they're like the special
Solutions right we had special solutions
to axal B now we've got special
solutions to differential
equations sorry we had special solutions
to ax equals z I misspoke
the special Solutions were for the null
space just as here we're talking about
the null space do you see that here is a
those two and what's the
dimension of the solution
space
is how many vectors in this basis
two the sign and
cosine are those the only
basis for the space by no means e to
theix and e to the minus I would be
another basis lots of bases but you see
that really what a course in
differential in linear differential
equations is about
is finding a basis for the solution
space the dimension of the solution
space will always be will be two because
we have a second order equation so
that's like there's 1803 in 5 minutes of
1806 is enough to take care of
1803 okay so there's a that's one more
example and of course the point of the
example is these
things don't look like
vectors they look like
functions but we can call them vectors
because we can add
them and we can multiply by constants so
we can take linear combinations that's
all we have to be allowed to
do so that's really why this idea of
linear algebra and basis and dimension
and so on plays a wider role
than
than than our constant discussions of n
byn
matrices okay that's what I wanted
wanted to say about that topic
now of course the
key uh number associated with matrices
to go back to that number is the
rank and the
rank what do we know about the
rank well we know it's not bigger than M
and it's not bigger than n so but I'd
like to have a little discussion on the
rank maybe I'll put that here so I'm
picking up this topic of rank one
matrices
and the reason I'm interested in rank
one matrices is that they ought to be
simple if the rank is only one The
Matrix
can't get away from us so for example
let me take let me create a rank one
Matrix okay suppose it's 3 suppose it's
2x3 and let me give you the
first
row what's what can the second row be
what tell me a possible second row here
for for this Matrix to have rank
one a possible second row is
2810 the second row
is a multiple of the first
row it's not independent so tell me a
basis for the oh yeah sorry to keep
bringing up these same
questions after the quiz I'll stop but
for now tell me a basis for the row
space a basis for the row space of that
Matrix
is the first row right the first row
145 a basis for the column space of this
Matrix is what's the dimension of the
column
space the dimension of the column space
is also one right because it's also the
rank the dimension you remember the
dimension of the column space equals the
rank
equals the dimension of the column space
of the
transpose which is the row space of a
okay and in this case it's one R is
one and sure enough all the columns are
all the other columns are multiples of
that column now there's there ought to
be a nice way to see
that and here it is
is I can write that Matrix as it's pivot
column 1
2 times
it's time
145 a column time a row one column time
one row gives me a matrix right if I
multiply a column by a
row that that's 2x one Matrix times a
1x3 matrix and the result of the
multiplication is
2x3 and it comes out right so what I
want to my my point is that rank
one
matrices that every rank one Matrix has
the form sum column times sum
row so U is a column vector v is a
column Vector but I make it into a row
by putting in V transpose so that's the
that's the
uh that's the complete picture of rank
one
matrices we'll be interested in rank one
matrices later we'll find oh their
determinant that'll be easy their igen
values that'll be interesting uh rank
one matrices are like the building
blocks for all matrices
and actually maybe you can
guess
and if I took any
Matrix a 5 by 17 Matrix of rank
four then it seems pretty likely and
it's true that I could break that 5x 17
Matrix down as a combination of rank one
matrices and probably how many of those
would I
need if I have a 5x 17 Matrix of rank
four I'll need four of
them four rank one matrices so the rank
one matrices are the are the building
blocks and out I can produce every I can
produce every five every rank four
Matrix out of four rank one matrices
okay that brings me to a question of
course would the rank four matrices form
a
Subspace let me take all 5 by 17
matrices and think about rank four M the
the subset of rank four matrices let me
I'll write this
down you see I'm I'm reviewing for the
quiz because because I'm asking the kind
of questions that are short enough but
that bring out do you know what these
words mean so I take my Matrix bace n
now is all 5 5 17
Matrix and now the sub the the question
I ask is the
subset
of of rank four mates
is that a
Subspace if I add a matrix of so if I
multiply a matrix of rank four by of
rank four or less let's
say because I have to let the zero
Matrix
in if it's if it's going to be a
Subspace but that doesn't just because
the zero Matrix got in there doesn't
mean I have a
Subspace so if I so the the question
really comes down to if I add two rank
four
matrices is the sum rank
four what do you
think no not usually not usually if I
add two rank four matrices the sum is
probably what could I say about the sum
well
actually well the rank could be
if it's a general fact actually that the
rank of a plus b can't be more than rank
of a plus the rank of
B so this would say if I added two of
those the rank couldn't be larger than
eight but I know actually the rank
couldn't be as large as eight anyway
what how big could the rank be for the
rank of a matrix in M could be as large
as right right so they're all sort of
natural ideas so rank four matrices or
rank one
matrices let me let me change that to
rank
one let me take the subset of rank one
matrices is that a vector
space if I add a rank one Matrix to a
rank one
Matrix no it's most likely going to have
rank two so this is so I'll just make
that point not a
Subspace
okay okay those are topics that I wanted
to uh just fill out the the previous
lectures I'll ask one more Subspace
question a more a more uh likely example
suppose I'm in let me put put this
example on a new
board suppose I'm in our in
R4 so my typical my my typical Vector in
R4 has four components V1 V2 V3 and
V4 suppose I take the
Subspace of
vectors whose components add to zero so
I let
s be all V all vectors V in four
dimensional
space
with V1 + V2 + V3 + V4 =
Z so I just want to consider that bunch
of vectors is it a Subspace first of
all it is a
Subspace it is a sub space what's how do
we see
that it is a
Subspace I formally I should check if I
have one vector that with whose
components add to zero and I multiply
that vector by six the components still
add a zero just six * 6 *
Z if I have a couple of V and a w and I
add them the components still add to
zero okay it's a
Subspace what's the dimension of that
space and what's the basis for that
space so you see how I can just describe
a
space and we we can ask for the
dimension as for the basis first and the
dimension course the dimension is the
one that's easy to tell me in a single
word what's the dimension of our
Subspace s
here and a basis tell me a tell me some
vectors in
it well I'm going to make you ask you
again to guess the
dimension again I think I heard it three
the dimension is
three how does this connect to
our axal Z is this the n space of
something is that the null space of a
matrix and then we can look at the
Matrix and and we know everything about
those subspaces this is the null
space of what
Matrix what's the
Matrix where the null space is then AV =
0 so I want this equation to be a =
z v is now the
vector and what's the Matrix that that
we're seeing
there it's the
Matrix of
41 do you see that that's that if I look
at AAL Z for this Matrix a I multiply by
B and I
get this requirement that the components
add to zero so I'm really at when I
speak about
s I'm speaking about the no space of
that
Matrix okay let's just say we've got a
matrix now we want it null
space well wait tell me it's rank first
the rank of that Matrix
is one thanks so R is one what's the
general formula for the dimension of the
null space the
dimension of the null space of a matrix
is in general an M byn Matrix of rank
R how
many independent guys in the null
space n- r
right N - R in this case is
four four columns the rank is one so the
no space is three dimensional so of
course you could see it in this case but
you can also see it here in our
systematic way of dealing with the four
fundamental subspaces of a
matrix so what actually what what are
all four subspaces then the RO row space
is clear the row space is in
R4 yeah can can can we take the four
fundamental subspaces of this Matrix
this's just kill this
example the row space is onedimensional
it's it's all multiples of that of that
Row the null space is threedimensional
oh you better give me a basis for the
null space so what the basis is for the
n space the special
solutions to find the special Solutions
I look for the free variables the free
variables here are there's the
pivot the free variables are 2 three and
four so the
basis basis for
S for S will be I'm expecting three
vectors
Three Special Solutions I give the value
one to that three
variable and what's the pivot variable
if the this is going to be a vector in
s minus one now the rows add to Z the
the entries add to zero the second
special solution has a one in the second
free variable and again a minus1 makes
it right the third one has a one in the
third free variable and again A minus
one makes it
right that's my answer that's the answer
I would be looking
for the a basis for the Subspace s you
would just list three vectors and those
would be the natural three to list not
the only possible three but the the
those are the special three okay tell me
about the column
space what's the column space of this
Matrix
[Music]
a so the column space is a Subspace of
r
one because m is only one The Columns
only have one component so the column
space of s the column space of a is
somewhere in the space R1 because we
only have these col colums are
short and what is the column space
actually I just it's just talking with
these words is what I'm
doing the column space for that Matrix
is
R1 the column space for that
Matrix is all multiples of
that column there
there's and all multiples give you all
of
R1 and what's the the remaining fourth
space the null space of a
transpose is
what so we transpose
a we look for combinations of the of of
the of the columns now that gives zero
for for a
transpose and there aren't any the only
thing the only combination of these rows
to give the zero row is the zero
combination okay so let's just check
Dimensions the null space has Dimension
three the row space has Dimension 1 3 +
1 is
the column space has Dimension One and
what's the dimension of this like
smallest possible space what's the
dimension of the zero space it's a it's
a
Subspace zero what else could it be I
mean let's we have to take a reasonable
answer and the only reasonable answer is
zero so one plus 0 gives this was
n the number of columns and this is M
the number of
rows and let's just let me just say
again then the the the Subspace that has
only that one point that point is Zero
Dimensional of
course and the basis is empty because if
if the dimension is zero there shouldn't
be anybody in the basis so the basis of
that smallest Subspace is the empty set
and the the number of members in the
empty set is zero so that's the
dimension
okay good now I have just five minutes
to to tell you
about well actually about some
some some this is now this last topic of
small world graphs and leads
into uh a lecture about graphs and
linear algebra
but let me tell you
the in these last minutes the graph that
I'm interested
in uh it's the graph where so what is a
graph better tell you that first okay
what's a
graph okay this isn't calculus we're not
I'm not thinking of like some sign
curve the word graph is used in a
complete different way it's a set of a
bunch of
nodes and
edges edges connecting the nodes so I
have nodes
like five
nodes and edges I'll put in some edges I
could could include them
all there's well let me put in a couple
more
there's a graph with five nodes and 1 2
3 4 five six
edges and some 5x6 Matrix is going to
tell us everything about that graph let
me leave that Matrix the next time and
tell you about the question I'm
interested in
suppose suppose the
graph isn't just just doesn't have just
five nodes but suppose every suppose
every person in this room is a
node and suppose there's an edge between
two nodes if those two people are
friends so have I described a graph it's
a pretty big graph 100 hundred
nodes and I don't know how many edges
are in
there there's an edge if you're friend
I so that's the graph for this
class a similar graph you could take for
the whole country so 260 million
nodes and edges between
friends and the question for that graph
is how many steps does it take to get
from anybody to
anybody what's what two people are
furthest apart in this friendship graph
say for the US by furthest apart I mean
the distance
from well I'll tell you my distance to
Clinton it's two I happen to go to
college with somebody who knows Clinton
I don't know so my distance to Clinton
is not one cuz I
don't happily or not don't know him
but I know somebody who does he's a
senator and so I presume he knows it
okay I don't know what your well what's
your distance to
Clinton well not more than three right
actually true you know me I take credit
for reducing your Clinton
distance uh what's your distance to
Monica uh not
um anybody below below four is in
trouble here uh or maybe three but uh
right so
uh what's Hillary's distance to mon I
don't think we better put that on the
tape
here one or two I
guess is that right I don't well we
won't
think more about that so
actually the the real question
is what's what are big large distances
who how how far apart could people be
separated and roughly this number six
degrees of separation has kind of
appeared it's a movie title it's a book
title and it's with this meaning that
that roughly
speaking uh six might be a fairly not
too many
people if you sit next to somebody on an
airplane you get talking to them you
begin to discuss mutual friends to sort
of find out okay what connections do you
have and very often you'll find you're
connected in like two or three or four
steps and you remark It's a small world
and that's how this expression small
world came up uh but six I don't know if
you could find if it took six I don't
know if you would successfully discover
those six in a in an airplane
conversation but here's the math
question and I'll leave it for next for
lecture 12 and do a lot of linear
algebra in lecture 12 but the qu the the
interesting point is that with a few
shortcuts the distances come down
dramatically that that uh I mean all
your distances to Clinton immediately
drop to three by taking linear Al that's
like extra bonus for taking linear Al uh
and to understand mathematically what it
is about these graphs or like the graphs
of the worldwide web there's a fantastic
graph so many people would like to
understand and model
the web what are the con where the edges
are
links and the nodes are are sites
websites uh I'll leave you with that
grab and I'll see you have a good
weekend and see you on
Monday